Next, we have Task 13.
Here we should implement a function
that sums a list of integers,
and that uses some sort of
divide and conquer approach.
That is, we should
use this 'splitAt' function to split
the list into two parts of equal size.
And then recursively compute the sum of
these lists and in the end combine them.
And we should only use one equation.
We can use guards but we cannot introduce
additional equations, for example,
with a where clause, so we are encouraged
to use let instead if we need a where.
Okay, so let's start by
giving the parameter a name.
And then let's think about the basic structure.
So we start with
splitting the list into a and b.
And let's just use the
function call from right here. Our
list is called xs in this example.
Okay, and now we also need to
give it the list parameter.
Now we have an a and a b and
these are two lists of integers.
Now you can also define the sum of a.
And the sum of b.
- Just for clarity as extra bindings -
And then we just say okay, sum a + sum b.
Okay, so that's our basic
divide and conquer approach:
We split the list into two equal parts
in the middle, that's what this div 2 here does,
and then we take the left part and sum it up,
take the right part and sum it up by a
recursive call, and then we combine the results.
Okay, so is that all?
Well, if we look at this test down
here, we see that sum [] should equal 0.
Well, that's not really encoded
anywhere here in our function.
So, let's add some guards to
make sure we catch this case.
Let's add the guard in case xs is the empty list.
So null xs would return True.
And the otherwise-case has our divide and conquer
scheme, and if our list is empty, we just return 0.
Okay, let's load this up.
Let's try it out.
So sum [] = 0. Okay, so far so good.
Let's check a list with one element;
oh, so nothing is happening.
Or maybe there's something
happening but it's not finishing.
Now we get a stack overflow.
So what's the problem here?
Well, let's take a look
at our splitting function:
We have a list with one element,
so this list has length 1.
And if we have 1 `div` 2, we get
0. Because this takes the division
and ignores the rest of the division
if it isn't a clear division.
Okay, so what we actually do is we do
splitAt 0 [1] in this case. So
this is what this (a, b) does.
So we end up with [] and [1].
And then we recursively call
sum [], this would return zero.
But now we call sum again on [1], which is what
we just did, so we have an infinite loop here.
Because for lists of length one, the
splitting does not produce any progress.
So we need to get an additional case.
If the length of xs is one, then we
just have one element in our list.
What's the sum?
Well, it's just that element, so this
one element is the head of the list.
Let's check that:
So now sum [1] is actually that
element (1) like we would expect.
Okay, so does it work for
lists with multiple elements?
Let's check some examples...
Okay, looks good.
You can check some bigger examples:
Let's sum all the numbers from 1 to 100.
This also looks right.
So this seems to work.
There exist some variations of this program.
For example, if we would like to calculate the
length of the list just once, we could try to
fit these two cases into one.
If we were allowed to use where, we could
do that and define something like...
... where n = length xs.
Then we can use n here and here.
But in this case, we are not allowed to do this.
So if we want to do the same kind of
refactoring, we just do it in the otherwise case.
So, we use let n = length xs.
And then we can use if to check if n == 1.
If this is the case, we return head xs.
And else
we do the divide and conquer strategy.
And now we have calculated length xs only
once. Not necessarily for performance reasons
but for readability and maintainability
of our solution, this is a good idea.
Okay, so that's that for Task 11.